<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         id="picketlink-idm-configuration">
  <title>Identity Management - Configuration</title>

    <section>
      <title>Configuration</title>
    
      <section>
        <title>Architectural Overview</title>
          
        <para>
          Configuration in PicketLink is in essence quite simple; an <code>IdentityConfiguration</code> object must first 
          be created to hold the PicketLink configuration options.  Once all configuration options have been set, you just create a 
          <code>PartitionManager</code> instance passing the previously created configuration.
          The <code>PartitionManager</code> can then be used to create <code>Partition</code> and <code>IdentityManager</code> instances.
        </para>          
          
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="diagrams/idm_config_architecture.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="diagrams/idm_config_architecture.png" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>
          The <code>IdentityConfiguration</code> is usually created using a Configuration Builder API, which provides a rich and fluent API for every single aspect of PicketLink configuration.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>
            For now, all configuration is set programmatically using the Configuration Builder API only. Later versions will also support a declarative configuration in a form of XML documents.   
          </para>
        </note>

        <para>
          The following sections describe various ways that configuration may be performed in different environments.
        </para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="programmatic_configuration">
        <title>Programmatic Configuration</title>
      
        <para>
          Configuration for Identity Management can be defined programmatically using the Configuration Builder API. The aim of this API is to make it easier to chain coding
          of configuration options in order to speed up the coding itself and make the configuration more <emphasis>readable</emphasis>.
        </para>
        <para>        
          Let's assume that you want to quick start with PicketLink Identity Management features using a File-based Identity Store.
          First, a fresh instance of <code>IdentityConfiguration</code> is created using the <code>IdentityConfigurationBuilder</code> helper object, 
          where we choose which identity store we want to use (in this case a file-based store) and any other configuration option, if necessary. 
          Finally, we use the configuration to create a <code>PartitionManager</code> from where we can create <code>IdentityManager</code> instances and start to perform Identity Management operations:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[IdentityConfigurationBuilder builder = new IdentityConfigurationBuilder();
        
builder
  .stores()
  .file()
  .supportAllFeatures();

IdentityConfiguration configuration = builder.build();

IdentityManagerFactory identityManagerFactory = new IdentityManagerFactory(configuration);

IdentityManager identityManager = identityManagerFactory.createIdentityManager();

User user = new SimpleUser("john");

identityManager.add(user);]]></programlisting>

        <section>
          <title>IdentityConfigurationBuilder for Programmatic Configuration</title>

          <para>
            The <code>IdentityConfigurationBuilder</code> is the entry point for PicketLink configuration. 
            It is a very simple class with some meaningful methods for all supported configuration options.
          </para>
            
          <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[IdentityConfigurationBuilder builder = new IdentityConfigurationBuilder();

builder
  .stores() // supported identity stores configuration
    .file() 
      // file-based identity store configuration
    .jpa()
      // JPA-based identity store configuration
    .ldap()
      // LDAP-based identity store configuration
  .contextFactory(...); // for custom SecurityContextFactory implementations]]></programlisting>

          <para>In the next sections we'll cover each supported Identity Store and their specific configuration.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section id="idm_security_context_configuration">
        <title>Security Context Configuration</title>
      
        <para>
          The <code>SecurityContext</code> plays an important role in the PicketLink IDM achitecture. As discussed in the <link linkend='idm_architecture_overview'>Architectural Overview</link>, 
          it is strongly used during the execution of operations. It carries very sensitive and contextual information for a specific operation and provides access for some of the 
          IDM underlying services such as caching, event handling, UUID generator for <code>IdentityTpe</code> and <code>Relationship</code> instances, among others.  
        </para>
        <para>
        	Operations are always executed by a specific <code>IdentityStore</code> in order to persist or store identity data using a specific repository (eg.: LDAP, databases, filesystem, etc). 
        	When executing a operation the identity store must be able to:
        </para>
        <para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
             		Access the current <code>Partition</code>. All operations are executed for a specific <code>Realm</code> or <code>Tier</code>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
             		Access the current <code>IdentityManager</code> instance, from which the operation was executed.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
             		Access the <emphasis>Event Handling API</emphasis> in order to fire events such as when an user is created, updated, etc.  
              </para>
            </listitem>
						<listitem>
              <para>
             		Access the <emphasis>Caching API</emphasis> in order to cache identity data and increase performance.  
              </para>
            </listitem>
						<listitem>
              <para>
             		Access the <emphasis>Credential Handler API</emphasis> in order to be able to update and validate credentials.  
              </para>
            </listitem>
						<listitem>
              <para>
             		Access to external resources, provided before the operation is executed and initialized by a <code>ContextInitializer</code>.    
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section>
        	<title>Initializing the SecurityContext</title>
          <para>
          	Sometimes you may need to provide additional configuration or even references for external resources before the operation is executed by an identity store.
          	An example is how you tell to the<code>JPAIdentityStore</code> which <code>EntityManager</code> instance should be used. 
        	  When executing an operation, the <code>JPAIdentityStore</code> must be able to access the current <code>EntityManager</code> to persist or retrieve data from the database.
        	  You need someway to populate the <code>SecurityContext</code> with such information. When you're configuring an identity store, there is a configuration option
        	  that allows you to provide a <code>ContextInitializer</code> implementation.
          </para>
       	  <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[public interface ContextInitializer {    
    void initContextForStore(SecurityContext context, IdentityStore<?> store);
}]]></programlisting>
				  <para>
				  	The method <code>initContextForStore</code> will be invoked for every single operation and before its execution by the identity store. 
			  		It can be implemented to provide all the necessary logic to initialize and populate the <code>SecurityContext</code> for a specific <code>IdentityStore</code>.
		  		</para>
	  			<para>
  					The configuration is also very simple, you just need to provide the following configuration:
				  </para>
       	  <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[IdentityConfigurationBuilder builder = new IdentityConfigurationBuilder();

builder
  .stores()
    .file()
      .addContextInitializer(new MySecurityContextInitializer());  
}]]></programlisting>
				  <para>You can provide multiple initializers.</para>
				  <note>
					  <para>
						  Remember that initializers are executed for every single operation. 
						  Also, the same instance is used between operations which means your implementation should be <quote>stateless</quote>. 
						  You should be careful about the implementation in order to not impact performance, concurrency or introduce unexpected behaviors.
					  </para>
				  </note>
				</section>
        <section>
        	<title>Configuring how SecurityContext instances are created</title>
        	<para>
        		<code>SecurityContext</code> instances are created by the <code>SecurityContextFactory</code>. If for some reason you need to change how <code>SecurityContext</code> instances are created,
        		you can provide an implementation of this interface and configure it as follows:  
        	</para>
       	  <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[IdentityConfigurationBuilder builder = new IdentityConfigurationBuilder();

builder
  .stores()
    .contextFactory(mew MySecurityContextFactory());  
}]]></programlisting>

				</section>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Identity Store Feature Set</title>
      
        <para>
          When configuring identity stores you must tell which features and operations should be executed by them. Features and operations are a key concept if you want to mix stores in order to execute
          operations against different repositories.
        </para>
        <para>
        	PicketLink provides a Java <code>enum</code>, called <code>FeatureGroup</code>, in which are defined all supported features. The table bellow summarize them:  
        </para>
        <table>
          <title>Identity class fields</title>
          <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Feature</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><code>FeatureGroup.agent</code></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><code>FeatureGroup.user</code></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><code>FeatureGroup.role</code></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><code>FeatureGroup.group</code></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><code>FeatureGroup.relationship</code></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><code>FeatureGroup.credential</code></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><code>FeatureGroup.realm</code></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><code>FeatureGroup.tier</code></entry>
              </row>
      		  </tbody>
      	  </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>
        	The features are a determinant factor when choosing an identity store to execute a specific operation. For example, if an identity store is configured with <code>FeatureGroup.user</code> we're saying
        	that all <code>User</code> operations should be executed by this identity store. The same goes for <code>FeatureGroup.credential</code>, we're just saying that credentials can also be updated and validated using 
        	the identity store.
        </para>
        <para>
        	Beside that, provide only the feature is not enough. We must also tell the identity store which operations are supported by a feature. For example, we can configure a identity store to support only
        	read operations for users, which is very common when using the LDAP identity store against a read-only tree. Operations are also defined by an <code>enum</code>, called <code>FeatureOperation</code>, as follows:    
        </para>
        <table>
          <title>Identity class fields</title>
          <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Operation</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><code>Featureoperation.create</code></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><code>Featureoperation.read</code></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><code>Featureoperation.update</code></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><code>Featureoperation.delete</code></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><code>Featureoperation.validate</code></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>
        	During the configuration you can provide which features and operations should be supported using the <ns:emphasis>Configuration API</ns:emphasis>. You don't need to be forced to specify them individually,
        	if you want to support all features and operations for a particular identity store you can use:
        </para>
     	  <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[IdentityConfigurationBuilder builder = new IdentityConfigurationBuilder();

builder
  .stores()
    .file()
      .supportAllFeatures();  
}]]></programlisting>
				<para>
					For a more granular configuration you can also use:
				</para>
     	  <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[IdentityConfigurationBuilder builder = new IdentityConfigurationBuilder();

builder
  .stores()
    .file()
      .supportFeature(
      	FeatureGroup.agent, 
      	FeatureGroup.user, 
      	FeatureGroup.role, 
      	FeatureGroup.group)  
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				The configuration above defines the features individually. In this case the configured features are also supporting all operations. If you want to specify which operation should be supported by a feature you can use:
			</para>
   	  <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[IdentityConfigurationBuilder builder = new IdentityConfigurationBuilder();

builder
  .stores()
    .file()
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.agent, FeatureOperation.read)
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.user, FeatureOperation.read))
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.role, FeatureOperation.create))
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.role, FeatureOperation.read))
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.role, FeatureOperation.update))
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.role, FeatureOperation.delete))  
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.group, FeatureOperation.create))
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.group, FeatureOperation.read))
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.group, FeatureOperation.update))
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.group, FeatureOperation.delete))  
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				For a more complex configuration evolving multiple identity stores with a different feature set, look at the example bellow:
			</para>
   	  <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[IdentityConfigurationBuilder builder = new IdentityConfigurationBuilder();

builder
  .stores()
    .ldap()
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.agent)
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.user)
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.credential)
    .jpa()
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.role)
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.group)
      .supportFeature(FeatureGroup.relationship)
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				The configuration above shows how to use LDAP to store only agents, users and credentials and database for roles, groups and relationships.
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
					Remember that identity stores must have their features and operations configured. If you don't provide them you won't be able to build the configuration.
				</para>
			</note>
      </section>

      <section id="idm_configuration_from_xml_file">
        <title>IDM configuration from XML file</title>
        <para>Actually it's possible to configure IDM with XML configuration. This possibility is good especially in case when
          you want Picketlink IDM to be part of bigger system and your users won't have a possibility to change source code and
          so they can't configure it programmatically with the Builder API. So they will just need to change the configuration in
          XML file instead of doing some changes directly in source code.
        </para>
        <section>
          <title>Unified XML configuration</title>
          <para>
            Whole Picketlink project provides unified format of configuration file, so that you can configure <link linkend='federation_overview'>federation</link>
            and IDM in same file.
          </para>
          <programlisting language="XML"><![CDATA[<PicketLink xmlns="urn:picketlink:identity-federation:config:2.1">

  <PicketLinkIDP xmlns="urn:picketlink:identity-federation:config:1.0"
                 ServerEnvironment="tomcat" BindingType="POST" SupportsSignatures="true">
    <!-- SAML2 IDP configuration is here -->
  </PicketLinkIDP>

  <Handlers xmlns="urn:picketlink:identity-federation:handler:config:2.1">
     <!-- Configuration of SAML2 handlers is here -->
  </Handlers>

  <PicketLinkSTS xmlns="urn:picketlink:identity-federation:config:1.0"
                 STSName="Test STS" TokenTimeout="7200" EncryptToken="true">
    <!-- Configuration of Picketlink STS is here -->
  </PicketlinkSTS>

  <PicketLinkIDM>
    <!-- IDM configuration is here -->
  </PicketLinkIDM>

</PicketLink>]]></programlisting>
          <para>Note that if you don't want to use Picketlink Federation, you can omit it's configuration and use just IDM.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>XML configuration format</title>
          <para>
            XML configuration is leveraging <link linkend='programmatic_configuration'>Builder API</link> and Java reflection during
            it's parsing, so names of XML elements are actually same like names of particular Builder methods.
          </para>
          <para>
            For example, let's assume that you want to use <code>FileIdentityStore</code> and your programmatic configuration looks like this:
          </para>
          <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[IdentityConfigurationBuilder builder = new IdentityConfigurationBuilder();

builder
    .named(SIMPLE_FILE_STORE_CONFIG)
        .stores()
            .file()
            .preserveState(false)
            .supportGlobalRelationship(Relationship.class)
            .supportAllFeatures();]]></programlisting>
          <para>Same XML configuration to configure IDM with <code>FileIdentityStore</code> will look like this:</para>
          <programlisting language="XML"><![CDATA[<PicketLink xmlns="urn:picketlink:identity-federation:config:2.1">

  <PicketLinkIDM>

    <named value="SIMPLE_FILE_STORE_CONFIG">
      <stores>
        <file>
          <preserveState value="false" />
          <supportGlobalRelationship value="org.picketlink.idm.model.Relationship" />
          <supportAllFeatures />
        </file>
      </stores>
    </named>

  </PicketLinkIDM>

</PicketLink>]]></programlisting>
          <para>You can take a look at <ulink url="https://github.com/picketlink/picketlink/tree/master/modules/idm/tests/src/test/resources/config">testsuite</ulink>
            to see more examples.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Bootstrap IDM from XML file</title>
          <para>
            So to initialize Picketlink IDM from XML you can use the code like this:
          </para>
          <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[// Replace with your own configuration file
String configFilePath = "config/embedded-file-config.xml";

ClassLoader tcl = Thread.currentThread().getContextClassLoader();
InputStream configStream = tcl.getResourceAsStream(configFilePath);
XMLConfigurationProvider xmlConfigurationProvider = new XMLConfigurationProvider();
IdentityConfigurationBuilder idmConfigBuilder =
  xmlConfigurationProvider.readIDMConfiguration(configStream);]]></programlisting>
          <para>
            Now you can bootstrap IDM from <code>idmConfigBuilder</code> in same way, like it's done in
            <link linkend='programmatic_configuration'>Programmatic Configuration</link>. Note that you can initialize builder
            from XML file and then you can do some additional programmatic configuration. For example, you may need to programmatically
            add <code>JPAContextInitializer</code> in case that you are using JPA, because you will need access to JPA <code>EntityManager</code>.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>            
</chapter>
