<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         id="picketlink-quickstarts">
  <title>PicketLink Quickstarts</title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
      Quickstarts are self-contained, concise examples that generally demonstrate at most one or two features. The
      PicketLink
      quickstarts at GitHub provide working, buildable code that shows the usage of a number of authentication,
      authorization and
      identity management features. They are a nice way to communicate the design, common and best practices and the
      usage
      of PicketLink.
    </para>

    <para>
      The PicketLink Quickstarts are part of the JBoss Developer Framework(<ulink
            url="http://www.jboss.org/jdf/quickstarts/get-started/">
      http://www.jboss.org/jdf/quickstarts/get-started/</ulink>), formerly known as JDF.
      There you can find a lot of useful stuff about Java, JavaEE and of course all JBoss projects and products.
      Also, there are a lot of useful information and tutorials that will guide you to configure and prepare your
      environment to start using any of the available quickstarts.
    </para>

    <para>
      All quickstarts are available at GitHub. So you can download them, fork the repository (if you have an GitHub
      account, of course)
      or even just clone the repository. The latter option is fully described along the README.md file for each
      quickstart, as
      well as a lot of additional information, configuration requirements, how to deploy and undeploy using the JBoss
      Enterprise
      Application Platform 6(and beyond) and so forth.
    </para>

    <para>
      The repository is located at<ulink url="https://github.com/jboss-developer/jboss-picketlink-quickstarts">
      https://github.com/jboss-developer/jboss-picketlink-quickstarts</ulink>.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        You don't need to be a Git expert in order to get the quickstarts. All the necessary commands are fully covered
        in the README.md file for each of them. For any additional information take a look at
        the JDF site too.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Available Quickstarts</title>

    <para>
      For a complete list of all available quickstarts, access the PicketLink Quickstart Repository.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>PicketLink Federation Quickstarts</title>

    <para>
      We have a plenty of quickstarts covering some of the most important aspects of PicketLink Federation: SAML based
      SSO,
      WS-Trust support and so forth. The repository for those quickstarts is located at<ulink
            url="https://github.com/picketlink2/picketlink-quickstarts">
      https://github.com/picketlink2/picketlink-quickstarts</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
      The best way to get those quickstarts up and running is using the <xref linkend="picketlink-overview-installer"/>.
      Usually, when using PicketLink Federation you don't ship the libraries inside your deployment, but you get them
      from the container where it is deployed. That is exactly what the installer does (among other things), it will prepare
      your JBoss EAP installation with the PicketLink JBoss Modules.
      The installer also performs some additional configuration to an existing JBoss EAP 6 installation in order to get the
      quickstarts up and running, such as changing your standalone.xml and deploying the example applications.
      Is just a matter of run the installer, start the server and start using the examples !
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        Users of PicketLink 2.1 series should start using the 2.5 version of the federation libraries. Once JBoss EAP is
        updated
        with the new module organization for 2.5 version, the 2.1 series will be deprecated.
      </para>
    </note>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Contributing</title>

    <para>
      PicketLink can be used to solve the most simple as well some of the most advanced security use cases. The main
      objective
      of the quickstarts is to cover most of use cases as we can, so people can quickly understand and start solving
      their own
      security-related problems based on what we're offering.
    </para>

    <para>
      We would be very glad to have your contribution to our quickstarts list. If you have any suggestion about a new
      example, please
      create a JIRA and describe what you're looking for:<ulink url="https://issues.jboss.org/browse/PLINK">
      https://issues.jboss.org/browse/PLINK</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can also contribute by sending a Pull Request to the PicketLink Quickstarts repository which the code of your
      example application.
      Just follow the Contributing Guidelines from<ulink url="http://site-jdf.rhcloud.com/quickstarts/get-involved/">
      http://site-jdf.rhcloud.com/quickstarts/get-involved/</ulink>.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>