<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         id="picketlink-idm-permissions">
  <title>Identity Management - Permissions API and Permission Management</title>
  
    <section>
      <title>Overview</title>
      
      <para>
        The Permissions API is a set of extensible authorization features that provide capabilities for determining access privileges 
        for application resources.  This chapter describes the ACL (Access Control List) features and the management of persistent 
        resource permissions via the <code>PermissionManager</code>.  It also explains how the <code>PermissionResolver</code> SPI 
        can be used to in conjunction with a custom <code>PermissionVoter</code> implementation, allowing you to plugin your own
        custom authorization logic.  
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The <code>Permission</code> interface is used in a number of places throughout the Permissions API, and defines the following
        methods:
      </para>

      <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[public interface Permission {

    Object getResource();

    Class<?> getResourceClass();

    Serializable getResourceIdentifier();

    IdentityType getAssignee();

    String getOperation();
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>
        Each permission instance represents a specific resource permission, and contains three important pieces of state:
      </para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <emphasis>assignee</emphasis>, which is the identity to which the permission is assigned.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <emphasis>operation</emphasis>, which is a string value that represents the exact action that the 
            assigned identity is allowed to perform.        
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Either a direct reference to the <emphasis>resource</emphasis> (if known), or a combination of a <emphasis>resource class</emphasis> and
            <emphasis>resource identifier</emphasis>.  This value represents the resource to which the permission applies.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Checking permissions for the current user</title>
      
      <para>
        The primary method for accessing the Permissions API is via the <code>Identity</code> bean, which provides the following two methods 
        for checking permissions for the currently authenticated user:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[boolean hasPermission(Object resource, String operation);
boolean hasPermission(Class<?> resourceClass, Serializable identifier, String operation);]]></programlisting>

      <para>
        The first overloaded method may be used when you have a reference to the actual resource for which you wish to 
        check privileges:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject Identity identity;

public void deleteAccount(Account account) {
    // Check the current user has permission to delete the account
    if (identity.hasPermission(account, "DELETE")) {
        // Logic to delete Account object goes here
    } else {
        throw new SecurityException("Insufficient privileges!");
    }
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>
        The second overloaded method may be used when you <emphasis>don't</emphasis> have a reference to the resource object, but you have it's
        <emphasis>identifier</emphasis> value (for example the primary key value of an entity bean):
      </para>

      <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject Identity identity;

public void deleteCustomer(Long customerId) {
    // Check the current user has permission to delete the customer
    if (identity.hasPermission(Customer.class, customerId, "DELETE")) {
        // Logic to delete Customer object goes here
    } else {
        throw new SecurityException("Insufficient privileges!");
    }
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>
        This method is generally used for performance reasons, for example when you don't necessarily wish to load a resource object
        because of a possibly expensive instantiation cost, or you wish to check whether there are suitable permissions assigned to
        the user before loading the resource.
      </para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>ACL Permissions</title>
      
      <para>
        An ACL (Access Control List) can be used to control which identities may invoke specific operations on application resources.
        Underneath the covers, ACL security checks are handled by the <code>PersistentPermissionResolver</code>, which reads the
        ACL entries for each resource via the <code>PermissionStore</code>, which is typically a wrapper around some form of persistent
        storage such as database table.
      </para>
      
      <section>
        <title>Managing ACLs</title>
      
        <para>
          ACL permissions are managed via the <code>PermissionManager</code>.  An instance of this bean can be obtained by first injecting the 
          <code>PartitionManager</code>, then getting an instance to the <code>PermissionManager</code> via the <code>createPermissionManager()</code>
          method:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject PartitionManager partitionManager;
        
public void managePermissions() {
    PermissionManager permissionManager = partitionManager.createPermissionManager();
}]]></programlisting>

        <para>
          Once you have a reference to the <code>PermissionManager</code>, you can use it to grant permissions:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[public void allowRead(User user, Customer customer) {
    permissionManager.grantPermission(user, customer, "READ");
}]]></programlisting>

        <para>
          The <code>grantPermission()</code> method accepts three parameters:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[void grantPermission(IdentityType assignee, Object resource, String operation);]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
          The <emphasis>assignee</emphasis> is the identity to which you wish to grant the permission.  The <emphasis>resource</emphasis> is the
          application resource for which the permission applies.  The <emphasis>operation</emphasis> is a String value representing the action that
          the assignee may invoke in relation to the resource.
        </para>

        <para>      
          Resources may conceivably be any type of <code>Object</code> so long as there exists a unique, serializable value that can be determined
          or in some way calculated from the resource object, which uniquely identifies that resource from other resources of the same type.  This
          unique value is called the <emphasis>identifier</emphasis>, an example of which might be the primary key value of an entity bean.  The
          <code>PermissionHandler</code> SPI (see section below) is responsible for generating identifier values for resource objects.
        </para>
        
        <para>
          The <code>revokePermission()</code> method is used to remove permissions.  Like <code>grantPermission()</code>, it also accepts three
          parameters:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[void revokePermission(IdentityType assignee, Object resource, String operation);]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
          It is also possible to revoke all assigned permissions for a single resource via the <code>clearPermissions()</code> method.  This is useful
          for example if you wish to delete the resource and don't wish to leave orphaned permissions:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[void clearPermissions(Object resource);]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
          There are also a number of overloaded methods available for querying permissions.  These methods take an assortment of parameters depending
          on exactly which permissions you wish to find:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[List<Permission> listPermissions(Object resource);

List<Permission> listPermissions(Class<?> resourceClass, Serializable identifier);

List<Permission> listPermissions(Object resource, String operation);

List<Permission> listPermissions(Class<?> resourceClass, Serializable identifier, 
                                 String operation);]]></programlisting>

        <para>
          Here's some examples:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[// List all permissions for a known Product
Product p = lookupProduct("grapes");
List<Permission> permissions = permissionManager.listPermissions(p);

// List all permissions for a Product where we know the resource class 
// and the identifier
List<Permission> permissions = permissionManager.listPermissions(
    Product.class, "bananas");

// List all "DELETE" permissions that have been granted for a Product
Product p = lookupProduct("apples");
List<Permissions> permissions = permissionManager.listPermissions(p, "DELETE");

// List all "UPDATE" permissions for a Product where we know the 
// resource class and the identifier
List<Permissions> permissions = permissionManager.listPermissions(
    Product.class, "oranges", "UPDATE");]]></programlisting>
      
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Configuring resources for ACL usage</title>
        
        <para>
          Every resource class for which you wish to support ACL permissions is required to have a corresponding
          <code>PermissionHandler</code>.  This interface is primarily responsible for the generation of resource
          identifier values, plus a couple of other utility methods (please refer to the API documentation for more
          details):
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[public interface PermissionHandler {

    boolean canHandle(Class<?> resourceClass);

    Serializable getIdentifier(Object resource);

    Class<?> unwrapResourceClass(Object resource);

    Set<String> listClassOperations(Class<?> resourceClass);
    
    Set<String> listInstanceOperations(Class<?> resourceClass);
}]]></programlisting>

        <para>
          There are two ways that a resource class can be associated with a <code>PermissionHandler</code> - the <emphasis>first</emphasis>
          way is by providing a <code>@PermissionsHandledBy</code> annotation on the resource class itself:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[import org.picketlink.idm.permission.annotations.PermissionsHandledBy;
        
@PermissionsHandledBy(CustomPermissionHandler.class)
public class MyResourceClass {
    
}]]></programlisting>
          
        <para>
          For the circumstances where it is not possible to annotate the resource class directly, the second way is to register a
          custom <code>PermissionHandler</code> instance for which the <code>canHandle()</code> method returns <code>true</code> for 
          the resource class:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[public boolean canHandle(Class<?> resourceClass) {
    return MyResourceClass.class.equals(resourceClass);
}]]></programlisting>

        <para>
          Registering a custom <code>PermissionHandler</code> is very easy - simply include it in your application deployment as an
          <code>@ApplicationScoped</code> bean, and it will be registered automatically.  Here's a complete example of a 
          <code>PermissionHandler</code> that allows permissions to be assigned to arbitrary string values (this handler is actually
          provided by PicketLink):
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[@ApplicationScoped
public class StringPermissionHandler implements PermissionHandler {
    @Override
    public boolean canHandle(Class<?> resourceClass) {
        return String.class.equals(resourceClass);
    }

    @Override
    public Serializable getIdentifier(Object resource) {
        checkResourceValid(resource);
        return (String) resource;
    }

    @Override
    public Class<?> unwrapResourceClass(Object resource) {
        checkResourceValid(resource);
        return String.class;
    }

    private void checkResourceValid(Object resource) {
        if (!(resource instanceof String)) {
            throw new IllegalArgumentException("Resource [" + resource + 
                "] must be instance of String");
        }
    }

    @Override
    public Set<String> listAvailableOperations(Class<?> resourceClass) {
        return Collections.emptySet();
    }
}]]></programlisting>
        
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Restricting resource operations</title>
        
        <para>
          For many resource types it makes sense to restrict the set of resource operations for which permissions might be assigned.  For example, 
          an application might have an entity bean containing lookup values for countries.  This <code>Country</code> bean is likely to only require 
          the bare minimum in terms of data management and so you might like to restrict the available operations for it to the typical <literal>CREATE, READ, 
          UPDATE, DELETE</literal> operations.  To do this we use the <code>@AllowedOperations</code> annotation - this annotation allows us to provide a
          child array of <code>@AllowedOperation</code> values that specify exactly which operation values that permissions can be assigned for:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[import org.picketlink.idm.permission.annotations.AllowedOperation;
import org.picketlink.idm.permission.annotations.AllowedOperations;

@Entity
@AllowedOperations({
    @AllowedOperation(value = "CREATE", mask = 1, classOperation = true),
    @AllowedOperation(value = "READ", mask = 2),
    @AllowedOperation(value = "UPDATE", mask = 4),
    @AllowedOperation(value = "DELETE", mask = 8)
})
public class Country implements Serializable {]]></programlisting>

        <para>
          The optional <code>mask</code> value can be used to specify a bitmask value to allow for more efficient storage of permission values.  If the
          mask values are set, the operation values for that object's permissions will be stored as a numerical value with the corresponding bit values
          turned on.  For example, if a single user was assigned permission for both the <literal>READ</literal> and <literal>UPDATE</literal> operations 
          for one of our <code>Country</code> beans, then this operation value would be stored as 6 (<literal>READ</literal> (2) + <literal>UPDATE</literal> (4)).
        </para>
        
        <para>
          The other optional value, <code>classOperation</code> can be set to <literal>true</literal> if the permission applies to the class itself, and
          not an instance of a class.  For example, you might wish to check that the current user has permission to actually create a new <code>Country</code>
          bean.  In this case, the permission check would look something like this:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject Identity identity;
       
public void createCountry() {
    if (!identity.hasPermission(Country.class, "CREATE")) {
        throw new SecurityException(
          "Current user has insufficient privileges for this operation.");    
    }

    // snip
}]]></programlisting>

        <para>
          This functionality is provided by the <code>ClassPermissionHandler</code> permission handler.
        </para>
      
      </section>
     
    </section>  
    
    <section>
      <title><code>PermissionResolver</code> SPI</title>
      
      <para>
      
      </para>
    </section>
    
</chapter>
