<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Identity Management</title>
  
    <section>
      <title>Overview</title>
      
      <para>
        PicketLink's Identity Management (IDM) feature provides a rich and extensible API for managing the users, groups and roles of
        your applications and services. The <code>org.picketlink.idm.IdentityManager</code> interface declares all the methods required to
        create, update and delete Identity objects and create relationships between them such as group and role memberships.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Interaction with the backend store that provides the persistent identity state is performed by configuring one or more
        <code>IdentityStore</code>s.  PicketLink provides a few built-in <code>IdentityStore</code> implementations for storing
        identity state in a database, file system or LDAP directory server, and it is possible to provide your own custom
        implementation to support storing your application's identity data in other backends, or extend the built-in implementations
        to override their default behaviour.
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="diagrams/identity_manager_stores.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="diagrams/identity_manager_stores.png" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject> 
      
      <para>
        Before PicketLink IDM can be used, it must first be configured.  See the configuration section below for details on
        how to configure IDM for both Java EE and Java SE environments.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Identity Model</title>
      
      <para>
        PicketLink's identity model consists of a number of core interfaces that define the fundamental identity types
        upon which much of the Identity Management API is based.  The following class diagram shows the classes and interfaces
        in the <code>org.picketlink.idm.model</code> package that form the base identity model.
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="diagrams/identitymodel.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="diagrams/identitymodel.png" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>      
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <code>AttributedType</code> is the base interface for the identity model.  It declares a number of methods for
            managing a set of attribute values, plus <code>getId()</code> and <code>setId()</code> methods for setting a 
            unique UUID value.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <code>Attribute</code> is used to represent an attribute value.  An attribute has a name and a (generically typed) value,
            and may be marked as read-only.  Attribute values that are expensive to load (such as large binary data) may be lazy-loaded; 
            the <code>isLoaded()</code> method may be used to determine whether the Attribute has been loaded or not.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <code>IdentityType</code> is the base interface for Identity objects.  It declares properties that indicate whether the
            identity object is enabled or not, optional created and expiry dates, plus methods to read and set the owning 
            <code>Partition</code>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <code>Agent</code> represents a unique entity that may access the services secured by PicketLink.  In contrast to a user
            which represents a human, <code>Agent</code> is intended to represent a third party non-human (i.e. machine to machine) 
            process that may authenticate and interact with your application or services.  It declares methods for reading and setting
            the <code>Agent</code>'s login name.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <code>User</code> represents a human user that accesses your application and services.  In addition to the login name
            property defined by its parent interface <code>Agent</code>, the <code>User</code> interface declares a number of other
            methods for managing the user's first name, last name and e-mail address.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <code>Group</code> is used to manage collections of identity types.  Each <code>Group</code> has a name and an optional
            parent group.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <code>Role</code> is used in various relationship types to designate authority to another identity type to perform
            various operations within an application.  For example, a forum application may define a role called 
            <emphasis>moderator</emphasis> which may be assigned to one or more <code>User</code>s or <code>Group</code>s to indicate 
            that they are authorized to perform moderator functions.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      
      </itemizedlist>
      
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Configuration</title>
      
      <para>
        Since PicketLink Identity Management is supported in both Java EE and Java SE environments, configuration details 
        has been split into the following two separate sections.
      </para>
      
      <section>
        <title>Java EE</title>
        
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Java SE</title>
        
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Getting Started</title>
      
      <para>
        The <code>IdentityManager</code> interface provides access to the bulk of the IDM features supported by PicketLink.
        To get access to the <code>IdentityManager</code> depends on which environment you are using. The following two
        sections describe how to access the <code>IdentityManager</code> in both Java EE and Java SE.
      </para>
      
      <section>
        <title>Accessing the <code>IdentityManager</code> in Java EE</title>
        
        <para>
          In a Java EE environment, the PicketLink Core module provides a producer method for <code>IdentityManager</code>, 
          so getting a reference to it is as simply as injecting it into your beans, as follows:
        </para>
      
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject IdentityManager identityManager;]]></programlisting>
  
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Accessing the <code>IdentityManager</code> in Java SE</title>
        
        <para>
        
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Managing Users, Groups and Roles</title>
      
      <para>
        PicketLink IDM provides a number of basic implementations of the identity model interfaces for convenience, in the
        <code>org.picketlink.idm.model</code> package.  The following sections provide examples that show these 
        implementations in action.
      </para>
  
      <section>
        <title>Managing Users</title>
        
        <para>
          The following code example demonstrates how to create a new user with username <emphasis>jsmith</emphasis>, first 
          name of <emphasis>John</emphasis> and last name <emphasis>Smith</emphasis>, with e-mail address 
          <emphasis>jsmith@acme.com</emphasis>.
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  User user = new SimpleUser("jsmith");
  user.setFirstName("John");
  user.setLastName("Smith");
  user.setEmail("jsmith@acme.com");
  identityManager.add(user);]]></programlisting>
  
        <para>
          Once the <code>User</code> is created, it's possible to look it up using its login name:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  User user = identityManager.getUser("jsmith");]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
          User properties can also be modified after the User has already been created.  The following example demonstrates how
          to change the e-mail address of the user we created above:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  User user = identityManager.getUser("jsmith");
  user.setEmail("john@smith.com");
  identityManager.update(user);]]></programlisting>
  
        <para>
          Users may also be deleted.  The following example demonstrates how to delete the user previously created:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  User user = identityManager.getUser("jsmith");
  identityManager.remove("jsmith");]]></programlisting>
        
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Managing Groups</title>
        
        <para>
          The following example demonstrates how to create a new group called <emphasis>employees</emphasis>:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  Group employees = new SimpleGroup("employees");]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
          It is also possible to assign a parent group when creating a group.  The following example demonstrates how
          to create a new group called <emphasis>managers</emphasis>, using the <emphasis>employees</emphasis> group 
          created in the previous example as the parent group:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  Group managers = new SimpleGroup("managers", employees);]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
          To lookup an existing <code>Group</code>, the <code>getGroup()</code> method may be used.  If the group name
          is unique, it can be passed as a single parameter:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  Group employees = identityManager.getGroup("employees");]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
          If the group name is not unique, the parent group must be passed as the second parameter (although it can still be
          provided if the group name is unique):
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  Group managers = identityManager.getGroup("managers", employees);]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
          It is also possible to modify a <code>Group</code>'s name and other properties (besides its parent) after it has
          been created.  The following example demonstrates how to disable the "employees" group we created above:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  Group employees = identityManager.getGroup("employees");
  employees.setEnabled(false);
  identityManager.update(employees);]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
          To remove an existing group, we can use the <code>remove()</code> method:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  Group employees = identityManager.getGroup("employees");
  identityManager.remove(employees);]]></programlisting>

      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Managing Relationships</title>
      
      <para>
        Relationships are used to model <emphasis>typed associations</emphasis> between two or more identities.  All 
        concrete relationship types must implement the marker interface <code>org.picketlink.idm.model.Relationship</code>:
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="diagrams/relationshipclassdiagram.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="diagrams/relationshipclassdiagram.png" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject> 
                    
      <para>
        The <code>IdentityManager</code> interface provides three standard methods for managing relationships:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  void add(Relationship relationship);
  void update(Relationship relationship);
  void remove(Relationship relationship);]]></programlisting>
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <code>add()</code> method is used to create a new relationship.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <code>update()</code> method is used to update an existing relationship.
          </para>
          
          <note>
            <para>
              Please note that the identities that participate in a relationship cannot be updated themselves, 
              however the attribute values of the relationship can be updated.  If you absolutely need to modify
              the identities of a relationship, then delete the relationship and create it again.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <code>remove()</code> method is used to remove an existing relationship.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <note>
        <para>
          To search for existing relationships between identity objects, use the Relationship Query API described later
          in this chapter.
        </para>
      </note>
      
      <para>
        Besides the above methods, <code>IdentityManager</code> also provides a number of convenience methods for
        managing many of the built-in relationship types.  See the next section for more details.
      </para>
            
      <section>
        <title>Built In Relationship Types</title>
        
        <para>
          PicketLink provides a number of built-in relationship types, designed to address the most common requirements
          of a typical application.  The following sections describe the built-in relationships and how they are intended
          to be used.  Every built-in relationship type extends the <code>AbstractAttributedType</code> abstract class,
          which provides the basic methods for setting a unique identifier value and managing a set of attribute values:
        </para>
        
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="diagrams/abstractattributedtype.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="diagrams/abstractattributedtype.png" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject> 
        
        <para>
          What this means, is that every single relationship is assigned and can be identified by, a unique identifier value.  
          Also, arbitrary attribute values may be set for all relationship types, which is useful if you require additional 
          metadata or any other type of information to be stored with a relationship.
        </para>
        
        <section>
          <title>Grant</title>
          
          <para>
            A <code>Grant</code> relationship is used to assign a <code>Role</code> to an identity type such as a <code>User</code>
            or <code>Agent</code>.  It is typically used to represent an <emphasis>application role</emphasis>, in which an entity
            is granted the privilege to perform certain restricted operations within the scope of an application or service.
          </para>
          
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="diagrams/grant.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="diagrams/grant.png" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject> 
          
          <para>
            The <code>IdentityManager</code> interface provides methods for directly granting a role.  Here's a simple example:
          </para>
          
          <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  User bob = identityManager.getUser("bob");
  Role superuser = identityManager.getRole("superuser");
  identityManager.grantRole(bob, superuser);]]></programlisting>
          
          <para>
            The above code is equivalent to the following:
          </para>
          
          <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  User bob = identityManager.getUser("bob");
  Role superuser = identityManager.getRole("superuser");
  Grant grant = new Grant(bob, superuser);
  identityManager.add(grant);]]></programlisting>
  
          <para>
            A granted role can also be revoked using the <code>revokeRole()</code> method:
          </para>
          
          <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  User bob = identityManager.getUser("bob");
  Role superuser = identityManager.getRole("superuser");
  identityManager.revokeRole(bob, superuser);]]></programlisting>
  
          <para>
            To check whether an identity has a specific role granted to them, we can use the <code>hasRole()</code> method:
          </para>
          
          <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  User bob = identityManager.getUser("bob");
  Role superuser = identityManager.getRole("superuser");
  boolean isBobASuperUser = identityManager.hasRole(bob, superuser);]]></programlisting>
        </section>
        
        <section>
          <title>Group Membership</title>
          
          <para>
            The <code>GroupMembership</code> relationship is used to represent an identity's membership of a <code>Group</code>.
          </para>
          
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="diagrams/groupmembership.png" align="center" scalefit="0"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="diagrams/groupmembership.png" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>           
          
          <para>
            A <code>Group</code> is typically used to form logical collections of users.  Within an organisation, groups are 
            often used to mirror the organisation's structure.  For example, a corporate structure might consist of a sales
            department, administration, management, etc.  This structure can be modelled in PicketLink by creating corresponding
            groups such as <emphasis>sales</emphasis>, <emphasis>administration</emphasis>, and so forth.  Users (who may represent 
            the employees in a corporate structure) may then be assigned group memberships corresponding to their place within 
            the company's organisational structure.  For example, an employee who works in the sales department 
            may be assigned to the <emphasis>sales</emphasis> group.
            Specific application privileges can then be blanket assigned to the <emphasis>sales</emphasis> group, and anyone who 
            is a member of the group is free to access the application's features that require those privileges.
          </para>
          
          <para>
            Let's start by looking at a simple example.  The following code demonstrates how we would create the hypothetical 
            <emphasis>sales</emphasis> group described above, and assign group membership to user "janet":
          </para>
          
          <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  Group sales = new SimpleGroup("sales");
  identityManager.add(sales);
  User janet = identityManager.getUser("janet");
  identityManager.addToGroup(janet, sales);]]></programlisting>
          
          <para>
            A <code>User</code> may also be a member of more than one <code>Group</code>; there are no built-in limitations on 
            the number of groups that a <code>User</code> may be a member of.  
          </para>
          
          <para>
            We can use the <code>removeFromGroup()</code> method to remove the user from the group:
          </para>
          
          <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  Group sales = identityManager.getGroup("sales");
  User janet = identityManager.getUser("janet");
  identityManager.removeFromGroup(janet, sales);]]></programlisting>
  
          <para>
            To check whether an identity is the member of a group we can use the <code>isMember()</code> method:
          </para>
          
          <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  Group sales = identityManager.getGroup("sales");
  User janet = identityManager.getUser("janet");
  boolean isJanetInSales = identityManager.isMember(janet, sales);]]></programlisting>
        </section>
        
        <section>
          <title>Group Role</title>
          
          <para>
            The <code>GroupRole</code> relationship type extends <code>GroupMembership</code> by adding a role property, and is
            used to represent identities that have a specific role within the context of a group. 
          </para>
          
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="diagrams/grouprole.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="diagrams/grouprole.png" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>   
          
          <note>
            <para>
              While the <code>GroupRole</code> relationship type extends <code>GroupMembership</code>, it does <emphasis>not</emphasis> 
              mean that a member of a <code>GroupRole</code> automatically receives <code>GroupMembership</code> membership also.
            </para>
          </note>
          
          <para>
            The <code>GroupRole</code> relationship type should be used when it is intended for an identity to perform a specific
            role for a group, but not be an actual member of the group itself.  For example, an administrator of a group of doctors
            may not be a doctor themselves, but have an administrative role to perform for them.  If the intent is for an individual
            identity to both be a member of a group <emphasis>and</emphasis> have an assigned role in that group also, then the identity
            should have both <code>GroupRole</code> and <code>GroupMembership</code> relationships for that group.
          </para>
          
          <para>
            The <code>IdentityManager</code> interface provides some convenience methods for managing group roles.  The following example
            demonstrates how to assign a group role to a user:
          </para>
          
          <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  Group doctors = new SimpleGroup("doctors");
  identityManager.add(doctors);
  User sally = identityManager.getUser("sally");
  Role admin = identityManager.getRole("administrator");
  identityManager.grantGroupRole(sally, doctors, admin);]]></programlisting>
  
          <para>
            The above code is equivalent to creating a <code>GroupRole</code> relationship manually, and adding it via the 
            <code>add()</code> method:
          </para>
          
          <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  Group doctors = new SimpleGroup("doctors");
  identityManager.add(doctors);
  User sally = identityManager.getUser("sally");
  Role admin = identityManager.getRole("administrator");
  GroupRole groupRole = new GroupRole(sally, doctors, admin);
  identityManager.add(groupRole);]]></programlisting>\
  
          <para>
            A group role can be revoked using the <code>revokeGroupRole()</code> method:
          </para>
          
          <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  User sally = identityManager.getUser("sally");
  Role admin = identityManager.getRole("administrator");
  Group doctors = identityManager.getGroup("doctors");
  identityManager.revokeGroupRole(sally, admin, doctors);]]></programlisting>
  
          <para>
            To test whether an identity has a particular group role, you can use the <code>hasGroupRole()</code> method:
          </para>
          
          <programlisting language="JAVA"><![CDATA[  User sally = identityManager.getUser("sally");
  Role admin = identityManager.getRole("administrator");
  Group doctors = identityManager.getGroup("doctors");
  boolean isSallyDoctorsAdmin = identityManager.hasGroupRole(sally, admin, doctors);]]></programlisting>
  
        </section>
        
        <section>
          <title>Authorization</title>
          
          
        </section>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Creating Custom Relationships</title>
      </section>
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Realms and Tiers</title>
      
      <para>
        If you are using PicketLink in Standalone mode, or if your application follows the ASP (Application Service Provider) model
        then you may wish to partition your users, groups and roles into Realms and Tiers.
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="diagrams/realm_tier.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="diagrams/realm_tier.png" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>   
    </section>

</chapter>
